Mary Lennox was sent to mleth Manor to live with her uncle everybody said she
was the most disagreeable looking child ever seen. It was true, too. She had a
little little thin face and a little thin body, thin light hair and a sour
expression. Her hair was yellow, and her face was yellow because she had been
born in India and had always been ill in one way or another. Her father had held a
position under the English Government and had always been busy and ill himself,
and her mother had been a great beauty who cared only to go to parties and
amuse herself with gay people. She had not wanted a little girl at all, and when
Mary was born she handed her over to the care of an Aya who was made to
understand that if she wished to please the me Sahib she must keep the child out
of sight as much as possible. So when she was a sickly,
fretful, ugly little baby she was kept out of the way, and when she became a
sickly, fretful, toddling thing she was kept out of the way also. She never
remembered seeing familiarly anything but the dark faces of her a and the
other native servants, and as they always obeyed her and gave her her own way in
everything, because the me Sahib would be angry if she was disturbed by her
crying, by the time she was 6 years old she was as tyrannical and selfish a
little pig has ever lived. The young English governs who came to teach her to
read and write disliked her so much that she gave up her place in 3 months, and
when other governesses came to try to fill it they always went away in a
shorter time than the first one. So if Mary had not chosen to really want to
know how to read books she would never have learned her letters at all. One
frightfully hot morning, when she was about 9 years old, she awakened feeling
very cross, and she became crosser still when she saw that the servant who stood
by her bedside was not her Aya Why did you come?" she said to the strange
woman. "I will not let you stay. Send my a to me." The woman looked frightened, but
she only stammered that the a could not come and when Mary threw herself into a
passion and beat and kicked her, she looked only more frightened and repeated
that it was not possible for the Aya to come to Missy Sahib. There was something mysterious in
the air that morning. Nothing was done in its regular order and several of the
native servants seemed missing, while those whom Mary saw slunk or hurried
about with ashy and scared faces. But no one would tell her anything
and her ey did not come. She was actually left alone as the morning went on, and at
last she wandered out into the garden and began to play by herself under a tree near the
veranda. She pretended that she was making a flower bed and she stuck big
scarlet habiscus blossoms into little heaps of earth, all the time growing more
and more angry and muttering to herself the things she would say and the name
she would call Sidi when she returned. "Pig! Pig! Daughter of Pigs!" she
said, because to call a native a pig is the worst insult of
all. She was grinding her teeth and saying this over and over again when she
heard her mother come out on the Vera with someone She was with a fair young
man and they stood talking together in low strange voices. Mary knew the fair young man who
looked like a boy. She had heard that he was a very young officer who had just
come from England. The child stared at him, but she stared most at her mother. She always did
this when she had a chance to see her, because the msai Mary used to call her
that oftener than anything else— —was such a tall, slim, pretty person and wore such
lovely clothes. Her hair was like curly silk and she had a delicate little nose
which seemed to be disdaining things, and she had large laughing
eyes. All her clothes were thin and floating, and Mary said they were "full of
lace." They looked fuller of lace than ever this morning, but her eyes were not
laughing at all. They were large and scared and lifted imploringly to the
fair boy officer's face. "Is it so very bad? Oh, is it?" Mary heard her say. "Awfully,"
the young man answered in a trembling voice. "Awfully, Mrs. Lennox. You ought to
have gone to the hills two weeks ago." The M Sahib rang her hands. "Oh, I know
I ought!" she cried.
"I only stayed to go to that silly dinner party. What a fool I was!" At that very
moment such a loud sound of wailing broke out from the servants' quarters
that she clutched the young man's arm, and Mary stood shivering from head to
foot. The wailing grew wilder and wilder. "What is it? What is it?" Mrs. Lennox
gasped someone has died," answered the boy officer. "You did not say it had broken
out among your servants."
"I did not know!" the me Sahib cried. "Come with me! Come with me!" and she turned and
ran into the house. After that appalling things happened, and the mysteriousness of the
morning was explained to Mary. The chera had broken out in its most fatal form
and people were dying like flies. The a had been taken ill in the night, and it
was because she had just died that the servants had wailed in the huts. Before
the next day three other servants were dead and others had run away in terror.
There was panic on every side, and dying people in all the bungalows. During the confusion and
bewilderment of the second day Mary hid herself in the nursery and was forgotten by
everyone Nobody thought of her, nobody wanted her, and strange things happened of which she knew
nothing. Mary alternately cried and S lept through the hours. She only knew
that people were ill and that she heard mysterious and frightening
sounds. Once she crept into the dining room and found it empty, though a partly
finished meal was on the table and chairs and plates looked as if they had
been hastily pushed back when the diners rose suddenly for some reason. The child
ate some fruit and biscuits, and being thirsty she drank a glass of wine which
stood nearly filled.
It was sweet, and she did not know how strong it was. Very soon it made her intensely
drowsy, and she went back to her nursery and shut herself in again, frightened by
cries she heard in the huts and by the hurrying sound of
feet. The wine made her so sleepy that she could scarcely keep her eyes open
and she lay down on her bed and knew nothing more for a long
time. Many things happened during the hours in which she slept so heavily, but
she was not disturbed by the whales and the sound of things being carried in and
out of the bungalow. When she awakened she lay and stared at the wall. The house was
perfectly still. She had never known it to be so silent before. She heard neither
voices nor footsteps, and wondered if everybody had got well of the chera and
all the trouble was over.
She wondered also who would take care of her now her Aya was dead. There would be
a new Aya and perhaps she would know some new stories. Mary had been rather tired of
the old ones. She did not cry because her nurse had died. She was not an
affectionate child and had never cared much for anyone The noise and hurrying about and
wailing over the Cera had fr frightened her, and she had been angry because no
one seemed to remember that she was alive everyone was too panic-stricken to
think of a little girl no one was fond of. When people had the Cera it seemed
that they remembered nothing but themselves. But if everyone had got well
again, surely someone would remember and come to look for her. But no one came, and
as she lay waiting the house seemed to grow more more and more
silent. She heard something rustling on the matting and when she looked down she
saw a little snake gliding along and watching her with eyes like jewels. She
was not frightened, because he was a harmless little thing who would not hurt
her and he seemed in a hurry to get out
of the room. He slipped under the door as she watched
him. "How queer and quiet it is," she said. "It sounds as if there was no one in
the bungalow but me and the snake." Almost the next minute she heard
footsteps in the compound, and then on the Vera They were men's footsteps, and the
men entered the bungalow and talked in low voices. No one went to meet or speak
to them and they seemed to open doors and look into rooms. "What desolation!" she heard one
voice say. "That pretty, pretty woman! I suppose the child, too. I heard there was
a child, though no one ever saw her." Mary was standing in the middle of
the nursery when they opened the door a few minutes later. She looked an ugly, cross little
thing and was frowning because she was beginning to be hungry and feel disgracefully
neglected. The first man who came in was a large officer she had once seen
talking to her father. He looked tired and troubled, but when he saw her he was
so startled that he almost jumped back. "Barney!" he cried out. "There is a
child here! A child alone! In a place like this! Mercy on us, who is
she!" "I am Mary Lennox," the little girl said, drawing herself up stiffly. She
thought the man was very rude to call her father's bungalow "A place like this!"
"I fell asleep when everyone had the chera and I have only just wakened up.
Why does nobody come?" "It is the child no one ever saw!" exclaimed the man, turning
to his companions. "She has actually been forgotten!" "Why was I forgotten?" Mary said,
stamping her foot. "Why does nobody come?"
The young man whose name was Barney looked at her very sadly. Mary even
thought she saw him wink his eyes as if to wink tears away. "Poor little kid!" he said.
"There is nobody left to come." It was in that strange and sudden
way that Mary found out that she had neither father nor mother left; that they
had died and been carried away in the night, and that the few native servants
who had not died also had left the house as quickly as they could get out of it,
none of them even remembering that there was a Missy Sahib. That was why the place
was so quiet. It was true that there was no one in the bungal
but herself and the little rustling
snake. CHAPTER two MISTRESS MARY QUITE